A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Asia Programs, Bangladesh, Dacca (Dhaka) Program Staff Files FA504
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Asia Programs, Bangladesh, Dacca (Dhaka) Program Staff Files
1971-1998
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA504
3.93 Cubic Feet 3 standard record storage boxes.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
Consultants and program files.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation maintained an office in Dhaka (formerly spelled as Dacca), Bangladesh from 1972 to 1997. Throughout the course of the Dhaka office's history, the Foundation's Bangladesh program focused on supporting projects and initiatives involved with food production, rural resource management, women's rights and opportunities, reproductive health and child survival, health and nutrition, employment and public policy, social science research and training, and arts and culture.
The Ford Foundation established its Dhaka office in 1972, a year after Bangladesh emerged as an independent country. Prior to 1971, the Foundation's support for East Pakistan was administered through its Islamabad, Pakistan office. During the mid-to-late 1970s, the Foundation annually committed about $1.8 million to its Bangladesh program (Foundation's program in Bangladesh memo from William Fuller to Haas, Miller, Perkins, and Thomas, September 29, 1978, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980 (FA739G), Report 019791).
- Consultants and Program Files, 1971-1995; I
  - Basic Documents Vol. I (1/2), 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Basic Documents Vol. II (2/2), 1972-1996 (Box 1)
  - Geoff Wood, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Leon E. Clark, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Geoffry D. Wood, 1975-1985 (Box 1)
  - Reports on BARD Consultancy (1/2), 1976-1987 (Box 1)
  - Reports on BARD Consultancy (2/2), 1976-1987 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Mark Pitt, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
  - Robert C. Terry Jr., 1979 November 15 (Box 1)
  - Shamim Hamid, circa 1980 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Nicholas Cohen, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Geoffrey D. Wood, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Hameeda Hossain, Roushan Jahan and Salama Sobhan, circa 1982 (Box 1)
  - V.C. Joshi (1/3), 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - V.C. Joshi (2/3), 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - V.C. Joshi (3/3), 1989-1995 (Box 1)
  - V. Fauveau and T. Blanchet, 1988 May (Box 1)
  - Kamla Chowdhry, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Martha A. Chen, 1989-1992 (Box 2)
  - Mary Zurbuchen, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - William Burch, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Marty Chen, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Asmeen Khan, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
  - Dr. Rounaq Jahan, 1989-1993 (Box 2)
  - Bhasicar Chandavarkar, 1990 November 22 (Box 2)
  - Grant Close-Out Memoranda (1/2), 1990-1994 (Box 2)
  - Grant Close-Out Memoranda (2/2), 1995-1998 (Box 2)
  - Najmul Huq, 1992-1995 (Box 2)
  - Anthony Bottrall, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Stephen F Minkin, 1993-1996 (Box 2)
  - Dr. James L Ross, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Alanddin Talukder, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Barbara Whitney, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - John W. Thomas, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Marshall Bear and Jennefer Sebstad, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Goutam Ghosh (Computer Disk), 1995-1997 (Box 2)
  - Roushan Jahan, 1993-1995 (Box 2)
  - Stephenie Hollyman, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Dr. A.F. Salahuddin Ahmed, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Peggy Bentley, 1996 May-June (Box 2)
  - Mark Sidel, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Steve Golub, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Rebecca Walker, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Ian Martin, 1971 February 28 (Box 3)
  - Rene Dumont - Short Notes on Some Villages and Some Problems, 1973 January (Box 3)
  - Ralph W. Nicholas - Some Uses for Social Anthropology in Bangladesh, 1973 July (Box 3)
  - Geoffrey D. Wood, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Shirley Lindenbaum - Social and Economic Status of Women in Bangladesh, 1974 April (Box 3)
  - Stephen D. Biggs - Bangladesh 1975, 1975 July (Box 3)
  - Lincoln C. Chen and Rafiqul Huda Chowdhury - Demographic Changes and Trends of Food Production in Bangladesh, 1975 October (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Pages, 1975-1990 (Box 3)
  - S. Bruce Schearer -- Fertility Control Technology in Bangladesh, 1976 March (Box 3)
  - Gustav F. Papanek -- Strengthening Economics at Dacca University, 1978 May (Box 3)
  - Nancy J. Piet -- Report on PCFP Directorate IEM Division, 1978 June (Box 3)
  - Gwatkin, Chowdhury, Pyle -- Health and Nutrition, Bangladesh -- Report to the Ford Foundation Dacca Office, 1980 February 1 (Box 3)
  - Stephen D. Biggs -- Review of Rural Poverty and Resources Programs, 1982 April (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation -- Employment and Income Generation, 1984 April (Box 3)
  - Administrative Background Materials, 1985-1992 (Box 3)
  - Ingrid M. Foik, 1988 October (Box 3)
  - Kamla Chowdhry, 1989 February (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation -- Bangladesh Strategy Paper on Women in Development, 1989 October 13 (Box 3)
  - Martha A. Chen -- Review of Ford Foundation Women's Programs in Bangladesh, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Enamul Haque -- Overview of Cultural Programmes in Bangladesh, 1991 October 25 (Box 3)
  - Dhaka Program Review, 1992 May (Box 3)
  - New York Appointed Staff -- Staff Salaries, 1992 January 18 (Box 3)
  - Dhaka Program Review, 1993 March (Box 3)
  - Gerard Rixhon -- Report to the Ford Foundation on Support for Human Resource Development, 1993 August 24 (Box 3)
  - Marshall A. Bear and Jennefer Sebstad, 1994 March (Box 3)
  - Dhaka Program Review, 1995 March (Box 3)